<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Harrington Shotgun]]></title>
  <link href="http://glevine.github.io/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://glevine.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2014-06-22T21:01:52-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://glevine.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Greg Levine]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How to Replace Bathroom Accent Tiles]]></title>
    <link href="http://glevine.github.io/blog/2014/06/22/how-to-replace-bathroom-accent-tiles/"/>
    <updated>2014-06-22T14:07:57-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://glevine.github.io/blog/2014/06/22/how-to-replace-bathroom-accent-tiles</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I&rsquo;m constantly bumping old knowledge out of my head, replacing it with new knowledge. I felt the need to be able to hold on to the old knowledge somehow. A blog seemed like the perfect forum. So, let the brain dumping begin&hellip;</p>

<p>We noticed some chipped accent tiles in our shower when we moved into our house. While watching the handyman replace the tiles, I realized that it didn&rsquo;t look so hard and I vowed to remember things like this so I would never have to hire someone to do it for me again &mdash; although some things are always better left to the pros. I just needed to write down what I was seeing because I&rsquo;ll never remember the nuances five years from now. As the man worked, I quietly typed everything he did into the Notes app on my iPhone.</p>

<h2>Materials</h2>

<p><strong>Thin-set Cement</strong> Quick Permaflex 570</p>

<p><strong>Grout</strong> Traditions Sanded Tile Grout</p>

<p><strong>Tools</strong> Razor blade, flat head screw driver, hammer, cardboard, sponge, cloth, and a saw or other cutting device for cutting tile.</p>

<h2>Remove the Broken Tiles</h2>

<p>Use a razor blade to score the grout around the tile. Use a flat head screw driver and a hammer to chisel out the old tile. Start about &frac34; to one side of the tile, in the middle, vertically, to avoid cracking other tiles.</p>

<p>As the tile is removed, or once it is completely removed, chisel and scrape away the remaining grout and thin-set. Use the screw driver and hammer to gently chisel along the edges of the adjacent tile to remove the grout.</p>

<h2>Install the New Tiles</h2>

<p>Estimate the size the tile should be &mdash; mark it with a pencil &mdash; and cut it to fit the hole with room for grout on all sides. It doesn&rsquo;t need to be an exact measurement.</p>

<p>Mix the thin-set. Apply thin-set to the back of the tile with your fingers and put the tile in place. Apply more thin-set if you need to remove the tile for adjustments, but only if necessary. Use your razor blade and fingers to remove any excess thin-set, as it shouldn&rsquo;t get on the front of the tile. Place small pieces of cardboard in the cracks between tiles to hold the tile in place. Wait about 10 minutes for the thin-set to dry.</p>

<p>Mix the grout. Use your fingers to apply the grout generously over the tile to fill in the edges around the tile. Use a wet sponge to gently wipe away excess grout. Repeat if more grout is needed to fill the gaps.</p>

<p>Wipe the tiles with a damp cloth to clean the surface. Use a razor blade to scrape away any grout that doesn&rsquo;t wipe off.</p>

<p>There you go. My first blog post. And we both should now have the ability to replace our own cracked or chipped bathroom tiles. Good luck to us both!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
